A Guide to the Powhatan County (Va.) Business Records, 1788-1891
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Powhatan County (Va.) Business Records, 1788-1891
Library of Virginia
27 volumes.
Powhatan County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Many of the business volumes are fragile and shold not be handled. please check alternative formats for volumes that have been microfiled. Please use microfilm if available.
Acquisition Information
These records came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Powhatan County in 2011.
Alternative Form Available
Please see Powhatan County Microfilm index in the Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm available on the Library of Virginia website for full listing.
Samuel B. and Francis O. Drake Blotter, 1840-1845 is available as microfilm Powhatan County (Va.) Reel 48
Cardozo, Oldner, and Company Sales Books, 1845-1846 is available as microfilm Powhatan County (Va.) Reel 48
John F. Cox Account Box, 1849-1859 is available as microfilm Powhatan County (Va.) Reel 48
William Campbell Scott Journal, 1842-1864 is available as microfilm Powhatan County (Va.) Reel 48
Forlines and Harris Account Book, 1853-1856 is available as microfilm Powhatan County (Va.) Reel 48
Henry W. Whitlock and Son Daybooks and Ledger, 1839-1846 is available as microfilm Powhatan County (Va.) Reel 48
George W. Williams Journal and Ledger, 1845-1848 is available as microfilm Powhatan County (Va.) Reel 48
Historical Information
Context for Record Type: Business records, volumes and loose records, are in some cases transferred to the Library of Virginia as components of court record transfers. These business records in some cases were simply stored in the local court building for safekeeping by business owners. In other cases, business records (particularly ledgers, account books, etc.) may have been filed in a court case as an exhibit. These business record exhibits appeared both in chancery causes and in judgments, these records serving as exhibits for business dissolution cases, debt suits, and contract disputes.
Locality History: Powhatan County was named for the Indian chieftain who ruled the Native American inhabitants of tidewater Virginia in the early seventeeth century. It was formed from Cumberland County in 1777, and part of Chesterfield County was added later. Its area is 272 square miles, and the county seat is Powhatan.
Scope and Content
Powhatan County (Va.) Business Records, 1788-1891, is comprised of various records created by individuals and companies is pursuit of documenting business activities in and around Powhatan County (Va.). Represented records largerly consists of bound volumes such as ledgers, account box, daybooks, account books and journals.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged
Series I: Samuel B. and Francis O. Drake Blotter, 1840-1845
Series II: Cardozo, Oldner, and Company Sales Books, 1845-1846
Series III: John F. Cox Account Box, 1849-1859
Series IV: William Campbell Scott Journal, 1842-1864
Series V: Davis General Store Daybook and Ledger, 1830-1834
Series VI: Elbert Mosby Tavern Account Books, 1837-1839
Series VII: John M. Stratton Daybook and Ledger, 1853-1854
Series VIII: Milton P. Atkinson & Company Ledger, 1829-1831
Series IX: Scott, Skipwith, and Cardozo Daybook and Ledger, 1854-1856
Series X: Unidentified Blacksmith Ledger, 1852-1855
Series XI: Unidentified General Store Account Book, 1891
Series XII: Unidentified Merchant Daybook and Ledger, 1804-1807
Series XIII: Unidentified Merchant Daybook, 1806-1807
Series XIV: Forlines and Harris Account Book, 1853-1856
Series XV: Henry W. Whitlock and Son Daybooks and Ledger, 1839-1846
Series XVI: George W. Williams Journal and Ledger, 1845-1848
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
See also: Powhatan County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1782-1938
Additional Powhatan County (Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
Contents List
- Samuel B. and Francis O. Drake Blotter, 1840-1845, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Samuel B. and Francis O. Drake General Store was located in the town of Macon, Virginia, and conducted business during the mid-19th century. The blotter was used as an exhibit in the chancery suit Executor of Francis O. Drake versus Administrator of Samuel B. Drake heard in the Powhatan County Circuit Court.
  Also see: Powhatan County Chancery Cause, Exr. of Francis O. Drake vs Admr. of Samuel B. Drake, 1850-008. Available Digitally through the Chancery Records Index.
  - Samuel B. and Francis O. Drake Blotter 1840-1845
- Cardozo, Oldner, and Company Sales Books, 1845-1846, 2 volumes
  Historical Information: Cardozo, Oldner, and Company was a partnership formed by John G. Oldner, William H. Cardozo, and James Gallagher on August 6, 1845. The general store was located at Powhatan County Courthouse. The partnership dissolved in the summer of 1846. The sales books were used as exhibits in the chancery suit John G. Oldner, etc. versus William H. Cardozo heard in the Powhatan County Circuit Superior Court of Law and Chancery.
  Also see: Powhatan County Chancery Cause, John G. Oldner, etc. vs William H. Cardozo, 1854-016. Available Digitally through the Chancery Records Index.
  - Cardozo, Oldner, and Company Sales Books 1845-1846
- John F. Cox Account Box, 1849-1859, 1 volume
  Historical Information: The account book was used as an exhibit in the chancery suit Edwin Fleming and wife versus Administrator of Frederick Hicks. It was heard in the Powhatan County Circuit Court. The suit involved the division of slaves owned by Hicks among his heirs.
  Also see: Powhatan County Chancery Cause, Edwin Fleming and wife vs Admr. of Frederick Hicks, 1859-002. Available Digitally through the Chancery Records Index.
  - John F. Cox Account Box 1849-1859
- William Campbell Scott Journal, 1842-1864, 1 volume
  Historical Information: William Campbell Scott was born in 1809 in Powhatan Company. He attended Hampden-Sydney College in 1823-1827. Scott graduated from University of Virginia Law School in 1829. He was a member of the Virginia House of Delegates in 1837 and 1851. Scott ran as Know-Nothing candidate in 1856 and was defeated. He was a lawyer in Powhatan County, colonel of the 102nd Virginia Militia Regiment, and brigadier general of the 4th Brigade, 1st Division, Virginia Militia. Scott was a member of the Virginia Secession Convention in 1861. He was appointed colonel of the 44th Virginia Infantry on June 14, 1861. He commanded the 44th during the Valley Campaign. Scott resigned his commission of the 44th on January 14, 1863. Scott died in Powhatan County on April 9, 1865. The journal was used as an exhibit in the chancery suits Polly R. Crawford vs. Executor of William C. Scott, etc., James Shipley and wife versus Executor of William C. Scott, etc., Administrator of Cleon A. Crawford, Jr. versus Executor of William C. Scott, etc., and Richard P. Crawford versus Executor of William C. Scott, etc. They were heard together in the Powhatan County Circuit Court. The suits involved Scott's failure to settle his accounts as guardian of Polly R. Crawford, Ellen R. Crawford, Cleon A. Crawford, Jr., and Richard P. Crawford.
  Also see: Powhatan County Chancery Cause, Polly C. Crawford vs Exr. of William C. Scott, etc.; James Shipley and wife vs Exr. of William C. Scott, etc.; Admr. of Cleon A. Crawford, Jr. vs Exr. of William C. Scott, etc. and Richard P. Crawford vs Exr. of William C. Scott, etc., 1870-014. Available Digitally through the Chancery Records Index.
  - William Campbell Scott Journal 1842-1864
- Davis General Store Daybook and Ledger, 1830-1834, 4 volumes
  Historical Information: William E. Davis, Joseph B. Davis, and perhaps Benjamin T. Davis operated a general store in Powhatan County, Virginia, during the early 19th century.
  - Davis General Store Daybook and Ledger 1830-1834
- Elbert Mosby Tavern Account Books, 1837-1839, 2 volumes
  Historical Information: Elbert Mosby owned a tavern that conducted business in Powhatan County, Virginia, during the early 19th century.
  - Elbert Mosby Tavern Account Books, 1837-1839
- John M. Stratton Daybook and Ledger, 1853-1854, 2 volumes
  Historical Information: John M. Stratton owned a general store that conducted business in Powhatan County, Virginia, during the mid-19th century.
  - John M. Stratton Daybook and Ledger 1853-1854
- Milton P. Atkinson and Company Ledger, 1829-1831, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Milton P. Atkinson & Company was a general store that conducted business in Powhatan County, Virginia, during the early 19th century. In 1831, Atkinson sold the store to Joseph B. Davis.
  - Milton P. Atkinson & Company Ledger 1829-1831
- Scott, Skipwith, and Cardozo Daybook and Ledger, 1854-1856 1854-1856, 2 volumes
  Historical Information: Scott, Skipwith, and Cardozo was a sawmill owned by William Campbell Scott, William M. Skipwith, and Abram J. Cardozo. It was located in Powhatan County, Virginia, and conducted business during the mid-19th century.
  - Scott, Skipwith, and Cardozo Daybook and Ledger 1854-1856
- Unidentified Blacksmith Ledger, 1852-1855, 1 volume
  Historical Information: The unidentified blacksmith shop was perhaps owned by Peter Talbot and conducted business in Powhatan County, Virginia during the mid-19th century.
  - Unidentified Blacksmith Ledger, 1852-1855
- Unidentified General Store Account Book, 1891, 1 volume
  Historical Information: The unidentified general store conducted business in Powhatan County, Virginia, during the late 19th century.
  - Unidentified General Store Account Book 1891
- Unidentified Merchant Daybook and Ledger, 1804-1807, 2 volumes
  Historical Information: The unidentified merchant conducted business in Powhatan County, Virginia, during the early 19th century.
  - Unidentified Merchant Daybook and Ledger 1804-1807
- Unidentified Merchant Daybook, 1806-1807, 1 volume
  - Unidentified Merchant Daybook 1806-1807
- Forlines and Harris Account Book, 1853-1856, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Forlines and Harris was a mercantile partnership formed by Derby B. Forlines and Norborne E. Harris that conducted business in Powhatan County, Virginia between 1853 and 1856. The account book was used as an exhibit in the chancery suits Norborne E. Harris versus Derby B. Forlines and Derby B. Forlines versus Norborne E. Harris heard in the Powhatan County Circuit Court.
  Also see: Powhatan County Chancery Cause, Norborne E. Harris vs Derby B. Forlines; Derby B. Forlines vs Norborne E. Harris, 1868-005. Available Digitally through the Chancery Records Index.
  - Forlines and Harris Account Book 1853-1856
- Henry W. Whitlock and Son Daybooks and Ledger, 1839-1846, 3 volumes
  Historical Information: Henry W. Whitlock and his son James M. Whitlock conducted a mercantile business called Henry W. Whitlock and Son in Jefferson, Virginia, from January 1841-January 1843. Prior to 1841, the business was solely owned by Henry W. Whitlock. Forlines and Harris was a mercantile partnership formed by Derby B. The daybooks and ledgers were used as exhibits in the chancery suit Executor of Henry Whitlock versus Frances E. Whitlock, etc., heard in the Powhatan County Circuit Court.
  Also see: Powhatan Count Chancery Cause, Exr. of Henry Whitlock vs Frances E. Whitlock, etc., 1870-010. Available Digitally through the Chancery Records Index.
  - Henry W. Whitlock and Son Daybooks and Ledger 1839-1846
- George W. Williams Journal and Ledger, 1845-1848, 2 volumes
  Historical Information: George W. Williams owned a general store located in the town of Jefferson, Virginia, and conducted business during the mid-19th century. The journal and ledger were used as exhibits in the chancery suit Binford and Nimms, creditors versus Administrator of George W. Williams, etc., heard in the Powhatan County Circuit Court.
  Also see: Powhatan County Chancery Cause, Binford & Nimms, creditors vs George W. Williams, etc., 1868-014. Available Digitally through the Chancery Records Index.
  - George W. Williams Journal and Ledger 1845-1848